Benjamin Franklin Papers Part 5 -- Letters to Franklin 1779 December-1780 December Mss.B.F85inventory05
American Philosophical Society
- Letters to Benjamin Franklin.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 June 21; L.S 4p.; Jones, Capt. John Paul. L'Orient
    Was informed at Versailles, by M. de Genet, that an express had been sent from court with the necessary orders to the King's officers at l'Orient respecting Captain Landais and the "Alliance." The evening before the "Alliance" had been towed to Port Louis; plans on the part of M. de Thevenard, the Commandant, to stop the "Alliance," even ordering the fort to fire upon and sink her, if necessary; his interference alone prevented such a catastrophe. The "Alliance" is now at anchor without, between Port Louis and Groa; has just sent Lieut. Dale with a letter to Capt. Landais. Account of a letter just received from Mr. Lee; is convinced he is disappointed at the failure of his plots to produce bloodshed between France and America. Yesterday sent a letter [3 p., in French] he wrote to Capt. Parke of the Marines on board the "Alliance," setting forth the fatal consequences which must follow, should they persist in this mutiny; also enclosed copy of Dr. Franklin's letter of the 16th to Capt. Landais and to the officers and people of the "Alliance," and desired an answer or a personal interview, and assuring them that they would, on returning to their duty, be done strict justice, and all his influences should be exerted to obtain their excuse for the past. Officers sent on board by the Commandant with the King's order for the arrest of Capt. Landais, who refused to surrender himself. Believes Lee and his party pretend to justify their measure by saying that Franklin did not put Capt. Landais under arrest, and that he cannnot displace him. Believes them to be English at the bottom of their hearts. Mr. Dale just returned with an impertinent answer from Capt. Landais.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 June 22; A.L.S. a copy has been made. L. in 3d P. 1p.; Dumas, C.G.F.
    Bewailing the sad news of the taking of Charlestown [S.C.]; opinion of the Grand Facteur, with whom he is finally reconciled.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 June 22; A.L.S. 1p.; Van den Yver frères and Co. Paris
    Acknowledging Franklin's favor of the 28th ult. with copy of the judgment of the ship "Flora" and her cargo; at present she is ready to sail for Holland but is detained until her passport arrives; begs Franklin to send it by the first courier to the Admiralty at Cherbourg.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 June 23; L.S. 4p.; Jones, Capt. John Paul. L'Orient
    Sale of the "Serapis"; Mr. Williams and himself now on the lookout for a freight ship to transport the remaining tone of public stores to America, after the "Ariel" is filled; believes that the Government might be willing to lend the "Serapis"; advantages to be derived from such a course; expects to have small difficulty in manning the "Serapis" and "Ariel." The Commandant has just sent a new requisition to Capt. Landais for the seamen who served with him (Jones) in the "Bon Homme Richard." Franklin's favor of the 17th inst. just received; thinks money would make the people of the "Alliance" do anything.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 June 23; L.S. 2p.; Adams, John. Paris
    Has just received a letter from the Comte de Vergennes on the subject of the Resolution of Congress of the 18th of March concerning the paper bills, in which he says that the Chevalier de la Luzerne has orders to make the strongest representations on the subject; thinks, if there is still time, these orders should be stopped, until proper representations can be made at Court; advantage the enemies of America will take of such a move.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 June 25; A.L.S. 2p.; Dumas, C.G.F.
    Efforts made to soften the effect of the bad news from America; his interview with the Russian Minister, Prince de Gallitzin; showed him Franklin's letter to the American privateers. Attempt made to burn the Russian fleet. M. Van Oudermeulen awaiting Franklin's reply to his letter.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 June 25; L.S. 1p.; Sartine, Antoine-Raymond-Gualbert-Gabriel de. Versailles
    Concerning the indemnity to be paid the owners of the corsair "Fair Play," which was sunk in trying to land at Guadaloupe; the decision of His Majesty to pay the owners fifteen thousand livres seems more than favorable, as the brigantine was only lost through the fault of her Commander, Captain Giddings.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 June 25; A.L.S. 3p.; Moylan, James. L'Orient
    Armed with Franklin's note and the two letters addressed respectively to Capt. Landais and Lieut. James Degge, went on board the "Alliance" accompanied by Jonathan Williams, and acquainted Capt. Landais that on his signing a receipt he would be given the letter; this the Captain refused to do on account of the letter being addressed to the late Commander of the "Alliance," therefore only delivered the other letter to Lieut. Degge. Threats made against himself and Williams by Landais.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 June 26; A.L.S. 3p.; Adams, John. Paris
    Reasons why he does not think Franklin has the right to remove Capt. Landais from the command of a ship committed to him by Congress; crying need of a proper tribunal to decide such disputes; advises Franklin to pursue the mildest measures, by transmitting all the evidence to Congress or the Navy Board for a trial by court-martial and ordering the commanding officer of the "Alliance," with the stores and convoy, to America. Encloses the three queries sent to him. [1 p.]
    Printed in Hale's "Franklin in France," I, 340.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 June 27; A.L.S. 1p.; Myrick, Joseph. St. Malo
    Has received a commission as Captain of the cutter, the "American Union"; having taken refuge in the above harbor, from an English ship, is detained there by the Commissary of the port, by order of M. de Sartine; applies to Franklin for protection; his crew as well as himself served formerly on board the "Black Prince"; disposition made of their prize-money.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 June 27; A.L.S. 1p.; Genet, [Edme Jacques]
    In accordance with the desire of Commodore Paul Jones, has had translated and sent to M. de Sartine all the papers in the enclosed packet.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 June 28; A.L.S. 1p.; Arendt, Baron d'
    Asks for a passage to America on board the "Alliance," all other ships filled; as he desires to pay for his passage and food, hopes his request will not be refused.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 June 28; A.L.S. 2p.; Puchelberg and Co. L'Orient
    Authorized by the officers and crew of the "Alliance" to act as their lawful attorneys and agents; asking for information in regard to the prize-money due this frigate.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 June 29.; A.L.S. 1p.; Adams, John. Paris
    Refers his correspondence with Count de Vergennes to Dr. Franklin.
    Printed in Diplomat. Corres. of Am. Rev., Wharton, III, 824.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 June 30; A.L.S. 2p.; Montluisant, Dominique-Louis de. L'Orient
    Through the recommendation of the Marquis de la Fayette, he has been granted by the King the post of lientenant of infantry; desires a passage to America on the "Alliance."
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 June 30; L.S. 2p.; Vergennes, Charles Gravier, comte de. Versailles
    Relative to Mr. Adams's letters in regard to France's position against the Resolutions of Congress of March 18. Accompanied by a duplicate of letter from Mr. Adams to Comte de Vergennes, dated Paris, June 16, 1780. (See LIV, 109.)
    (In French. Copy.)
    Printed in Diplomat. Corres. of Am. Rev., Wharton, III, 827.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 June 30; L. in 3d P. 1p.; Rayneval, Joseph Gérard de
    Enclosing Mr. Adam's original letter; begs for its return after a copy has been made.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 June; A.L.S. 4p.; John de Neufville and Son. Amsterdam
    Wrote by the last mail announcing that they were willing to protect the American credit by accepting provisionally certain bills drawn on Henry Laurens by order of Congress; explanation of the whole matter.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1780.] July 1; A.L.S. 1p.; Amezaga, Ignore d'Urtado, marquis d'
    Making an appointment to dine with Franklin; hears of him often from M. Amelot.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 July 1; A.L.S. 1p.; Johnson, Joshua. Nantes
    When he accepted the appointment of Congress, was not aware that he was exepected to leave his family and business to attend to that of the public, without even his expenses being defrayed; will write Congress that he cannot possibly accept the trust on such terms. Is much obliged for the information about the business of the State of Maryland.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 July 2; L.S. 1p.; The Crew of the "Bon Homme Richard." On board the "Alliance."
    Complaining that they have been in irons since Wednesday last and also on half rations; determined to remain prisoners until they go to America, unless Franklin will extricate them from their unhappy situation.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 July 2; A.L.S. 3p.; Landais, Capt. Pierre. On board the "Alliance" at Groa
    Enumerates the prizes taken and finds fault with the delay in selling them. All his people have been hard at work since he took command and he has heard no mutinous declarations; informed that Capt. Jones conversed with the officers and crew of the "Alliance"; desires that he should be reprimanded; will sail as soon as his people are paid; expects to answer for his conduct to those who gave him command of the "Alliance".
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 July 1; L.S. 2p.; Sonnemaens, Col. M. de (M.A.'s husband). Venlo
    Is surprised that his brother, Baren de Wülff[en], did not follow the good council and advice given him; anxious for him to come to Venlo and remain there till all his wounds are healed.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 July 4; A.L.S. 2p.; Dumas, C.G.F.
    Sent Franklin's letter to M. Van Oudermeulen. State of affairs in Holland; two opposing parties, one in favor of strengthening the army, the other, the navy. His own unhappy situation. Rumors current that Landais has taken possession of Jones's vessel, the "Alliance," in virtue of his American commission.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 July 4; A.L.S. 1p.; Kelly, Timothy. St. Malo
    Forced to embark on the cutter, the "American Union" under a French commission; this vessel at present detained at St. Malo by order of the Ministry; such treatment will prevent the Irish from joining the American cause; begs for justice.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 July 5; A.L.S. 3p.; Demayr, -----
    Is a Prussian officer who wishes to serve in the American army.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 July 5; A.L.S. 1p.; Valory, Charles-Jean-Marie de. Bordeaux
    Concerning a large sum of money placed by him with Congress; desires to know if any interest will be paid him and when he may hope to be paid the principal.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 July 5; A.L.S. 2p.; Jones, Capt. John Paul. L'Orient
    Since the 23rd ult., has been doing his best to counteract the schemes of Landais and his party; enclosing copies of his letters to M. de Thevenard (1 p.) and to the crew of the "Alliance" (2 p.). Account of Mr. Blodget, purser of the "Alliance," having given himself up as a voluntary prisoner rather than attend him (Jones) on board the "Ariel" for the purpose of going over the accounts of the crew of the "Alliance," Thinks the crew will not weigh anchor until they are hopeless of receiving their money. Honored with Franklin's favor of the 27th ult.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 July 6; A.L.S. 2p.; Dumas, C.G.F.
    Arrival of Mr. Issac White, of Salem, and Mr. Ed[ward] Jones, of Boston; account of their voyage; Americans undismayed by the taking of Charlestown; obliged to throw their letters and despatches overboard, owing to the extraordinary conduct of the French corsair, "La Princesse de Robec," Capt. Cornu.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 July 7; A.L.S. 3p.; John Diot and Co. Morlaix
    Details of the cruise of the "Black Princess"; captured eight prizes which Capt. Macatter was forced to ransom, owing to the weakness of his crew; took the brig "Padmore"; hopes her judgment and condemnation will be issued soon.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 July 7; A.L.S. 1p.; Dumas, C.G.F.
    Busy translating the Protest of the minority of the Chapter of Munster, in order to send it to him; important contents of this paper. [3 p.]
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 July 7; D. 3p.; Dumas, C.G.F.
    Copy of a protest made by the minority in the Chapter of June 16th, 1780 against the election of a Prince of the House of Austria as coadjutor to the Grand Elector of the High Chapter.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 July 7; A.L.S. 1p.; Wulffen (Wolff), Jean Henry, baron de. Venlo
    He expects to rest and recuperate; desires nothing more than to return to his post; will therefore hold himself in readiness for Franklin's further orders.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 July 7; A.L.S. 2p.; Landais, Capt. Pierre. On board the "Alliance" at Groa
    Not having received Franklin's order for sailing, and seeing no prospect of having his people righted, is determined to seek justice for them in their own country; is getting under sail at once.
    Printed in Hale's Franklin in France, I, 339.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 July 10; A.L.S. 2p.; Arros d'Argelos, Jean-François, baron d'. Versailles
    Has received no answer from Franklin to the letter written by Mme. de la Fayette in regard to his voyage to Boston.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 July 10; A.L.S. 3p.; Assarts, Louis-Germain Dupin d'. Assarts
    A retired officer who asks to shed his blood for the United States.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 July 10; L.S. 2p.; Puchelberg and Co. L'Orient
    M. de Chaumont's responsibility for prize-money due the "Alliance"; M. Schweighauser will send Franklin the account of the furnitures they were obliged to make the "Alliance" for account of Congress.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 July 12; A.L.S. 2p.; Lebègue de Presle, Achille-Guillaume
    Thinks he has found a suitable place for the young American doctor.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 July 12; L.S. 3p.; Huntington, Samuel. Philadelphia
    Introducing the Hon. James Searle; is a member of Congress for Pennsylvania who goes to Europe charged with business of importance from that State; amount of bills which will be presented by Mr. Searle. The news of the siege and capitulation of Charlestown [,S. C.] will probably arrive before this letter.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 July 12; L.S. 2p.; Jones, Capt. John Paul. L'Orient
    Defends his conduct in leaving the "Alliance" and going up to Paris. Considers the delay in distributing the prize-money was the primary cause of the whole trouble with the "Alliance"; part played in the affair by Mr. Lee; under the circumstances believes that Tourville himself could not have prevented the plot from succeeding. If he had sufficient seamen, could be ready for sea in three days. Wages and prize-money due the crew of the "Bon Homme Richard."
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 July 13; A.L.S. 3p.; Dyke, Charles de. Stralsund
    Anxious to enter the American army with a rank not less than First Lieutenant.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 July 13; L. in 3d P. 1p.; Jackson, E. Paris
    As a near relation of Dr. Cadwalader, of Philadelphia, desires an audience; sends by bearer the London papers from June 20th to July 4th.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 July 13; A.L.S. 4p.; John de Neufville and Son. Amsterdam
    Discusses ways of procuring money for the payment of certain bills, should these be closed; question of making a loan in Holland; a proposition of their own for solving the difficulty.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 July 14; A.L.S. 2p.; Mease, Robert. L'Orient
    In accordance with a letter just received from Jonathan Williams, gives information respecting the comparative value of hard money, bills of exchange and the circulating currency of America at the time of his departure from Philadelphia.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 July 14; L.S. 3p.; Jacqué, -----. Châtillon-sur-Sèvre
    Concerning the cure for dropsy.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 July 14; A.L.S. 3p.; Roberdeau, Jacques-Dominique. Haguenau
    Begs Franklin to procure a passage to America for his son who wishes to serve with their relative, Gen. Daniel de Roberdeau; enclosing an introductory letter for his son from M. de Barth, Syndic-General of the Province of Alsace (1 p.).
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 July 14; L in 3d P. 1p.; Le Roy, Jean Baptiste
    He and M. de Maillebois, on the 20th of the month, will wait upon Dr. Franklin.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 July 15; A.L.S. 1p.; Sudlin, Alexis
    Having been unable to see Franklin, left a letter from the gentleman who received permission to paint Franklin's portrait.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 July 17; A.L.S. 1p.; Brent, W. Liège
    Requesting that the enclosed letters may be forwarded; supposes Franklin has heard of the battles in the West Indies, and the defeat of the Americans.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 July 17; A.L.S. 1p.; Grand, Henry. Paris
    Left with Mr. Williams a memorandum of payments which seemed to refer to Franklin's private expenses. Encloses an order drawn upon Mr. Deane and himself for £3,600, which he thinks Franklin must have forgotten.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 July 17; A.L.S. 1p.; Cooper, Samuel. Boston
    Fears that the vessel in which Mr. Austin sailed has been lost. The bearer of this is the son of Henry Bromfield, Esq., who goes to England and France to settle his father's accounts; begs Franklin to assist him in the recovery of his property.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 Sept. 18; L.S. Roque, Ven[era]ble Exercice. 3p.; The Loge Des Commandeuzs de Temple Carcassonne
    Thanking Dr. Franklin for the interest taken by him in the Andrieu family on their recommendation. Request him to continue his good offices. Inform him of the election of Prince Nicolas de Galitzin to the head of their Lodge. Invite Dr. Franklin to become affiliated with their temple.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 July 19; A.L.S. 2p.; Ross, Jno. L'Orient
    The delays and difficulties in getting forward the stores, due to the disturbance on board the "Alliance." The "Ariel" only able to carry half the arms ordered. Advisability of recommending the brig "St. Luke" to the protection of Capt. Jones as well as any others sailing at the same time.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1786 July 19; L. in 3d P. 1p.; Clermont-Tonnerre, Anne-Marie-Louise Bernard de Boulainvilliers, vicomtesse de ("Mlle de Passy"). Passy
    Begs to have two letters forwarded from le Chevalier de Feuilly who served some time in the American army.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 July 20; A.L.S. 2p.; Dumas, C.G.F.
    Blames Jones for the trouble on the "Alliance." Denmark about to declare herself in favor of an armed neutrality. Loan made to the Baron de Wülffen.
    (In French, partly in cipher, deciphered.)
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 July 22; A.L.S. 2p.; Dalton, Tristram. Boston
    Concerning the payment of indemnity, ordered by the King of France, to Captain Giddings for the loss of the brigantine "Fair Play."
  - to ----- Fallavel, 1780 July 22; A.L.S. 3p.; Dezoteux, Capt. L'Orient
    Desires the letters of recommendation promised him; sails with Captain Jones in a few days.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 July 22; L.S. 2p.; Esser, H. Venlo
    At the desire of M. de Wülffen, writes for the position of Captain, with three month's pay in advance; would like to join M. de Wülffen, who is on the point of returning to America.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 July 24; A.L.S. 3p.; John Diot and Co. Morlaix
    The arrival of the prize "Padmore," Capt. Solomon Williams; forwarding abstract of the journal of the "Black Princess," Capt. Macatter, Commander, who expects that the prisoners taken will be exchanged for Americans now lying in English jails.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 July 24.; L.S. 1p.; Champion, -----. Paris
    Offering to furnish the American troops with clothing, at a moderate figure.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 July 24; L.S. 1p.; Magniel Montauban and Co. Paris
    Offering to furnish the American troops with uniforms in accordance with any given model; enclosing price-list.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 July 25; A.L.S. 1p.; Brent, W. Liège
    His countrymen in high spirits; just had despatches from the English of the capture of Fort St. John [Folrida], in America, from the Spaniards; accounts from Cornwallis of further successes in South Carolina.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 July 25; A.L.S. 2p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Arrival of a cartel at Morlaix; encloses a letter from Capt. [John] Manley; poor Cunningham still alive; wishes all these poor fellows could be exchanged; artifices used by the English to induce the prisoners to enter their service.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 July 25; A.L.S. 2p.; Jean, Mr Robeson's negro. Le Petit Oatelet
    Begs his intercession with Captain [William] Robeson.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 July 25; A.L.S. 3p.; Cooper, Samuel. Boston
    Offering his congratulations upon the safe arrival of the entire fleet from Brest, under the Chevalier de Ternay. News of the loss of Charlestown will arrive before his letter; General Lincoln and his whole army made prisoners and four frigates taken; difficulty of sending aid and supplying provisions caused the surrender. This loss and the arrival of the Marquis de la Fayette have awakened the States; great efforts being made to reinforce Gen. Washington's army. Barbarous conduct of the English in the Jerseys nobly opposed by Gen. [Nathanael] Greene with a handful of troops and the Jersey militia; Mrs. Calder, the wife of a clergyman-cruelly murdered and many women abused. Report of a British fleet off Newport; supposed to be Graves joined with Arbuthnot. The bearer of this is his nephew, Richard Cooper, who has been some time in the naval service of his country. Recommends to Franklin's kindness his dear boy at Passy.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 July 25; A.L.S. 3p.; Raspe, Rudolph Erich. London
    Recommending Baron Podmaniczki, a Hungarian noble who has been received with great distinction by the nobility and learned of London; admitted to the Royal Society and, according to the new principle, was taxed thirty guineas. Dr. [James] Graham, the prince of quacks has set up a Temple of Health in the Adelphi and pretends to do wonders with his electrical, magnetical, aerial, aetherial and musical influences. Mr. [David] Williams's lectures on Universal Toleration and Benevolence not productive of much result so far.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, c. 1780 July 25; L.S. 4p.; Barbançon, comte de
    Successful planting of the pineapple sent him by Franklin. Fears his letter to Mr. Bartram, with Franklin's letter of recommendation, never reached its destination; sends another letter to which he begs him to add a few lines; offers to procure any plant which he desires cultivated in America.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 July 26; L. in 3d P. 1p.; Fallavel, ------
    Request for a letter of recommendation for M. Dezoteux.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 July 28; L.S. 3p.; Macatter, Capt Edward. Morlaix
    Concerning his eighteen prisoners now in jail at Morlaix; the Commissary proposes to send them by the "Britannia," cartel ship, for exchange; prefers keeping them there rather than send them to England, on account of the uncertainty of thier being exchanged for Americas; not a single man would sail with him did they not count upon the certainity of exchange.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 July 28; A.L.S. 2p.; Illens, ----- de. Marseilles